today, no animal had killed another animal. Not even a rat had been killed.
They had made the
They had made their way onto the little knoll where the half-finished windmill
stood. And with one accord, they all lay down as though huddling together for warmth.
Clover, Muriel, Benjamin, the cows, the sheep, and a whole flock of geese and hens.
Everyone, indeed, except the cat, who had suddenly disappeared just before
Napoleon ordered the animals to assemble.
For some time, nobody spoke.
Only Boxer remained on his feet. He fidgeted to and fro, swishing his long
black tail against his sides, and occasionally uttering a little whinny of surprise.
Finally, he said, >> "I do not understand it. I would not have believed that such things could
happen on our farm.
It must be due to some fault in ourselves.
The solution, as I see it, is to work harder.
From now onwards, I shall get up a full hour earlier in the mornings."
>> And he moved off at his lumbering trot and made for the quarry.
Having got there, he collected two successive loads of stone and dragged
them down to the windmill before retiring for the night.
The animals huddled about Clover, not speaking.
The knoll where they were lying gave them a wide prospect across the countryside.
Most of Animal Farm was within their view.
The long pasture, stretching down to the main road, the hayfield, the spinney,
the drinking pool, the plowed fields where the young wheat was thick and
green, and the red roofs of the farm buildings with the smoke curling from the chimneys.
It was a clear spring evening.
The grass and the bursting hedges were gilded by the level rays of the sun.
Never had the farm, and with a kind of surprise they remembered that it was
their own farm, every inch of it their own property, appeared to the animals so desirable a
place.
As Clover looked down the hillside, her eyes filled with tears.
If she could have spoken her thoughts, it would have been to say that this was
not what they had aimed at when they had set themselves years ago to work for the
overthrow of the human race.
These scenes of terror and slaughter were not what they had looked forward to
on that night when old Major first stirred them to rebellion.
If she herself had had any picture of the future, it had been of a society of
animals set free from hunger and the whip.
All equal, each working according to his capacity, the strong protecting the
weak, as she had protected the lost brood of ducklings with her foreleg on
the night of Major's speech.
Instead, she did not know why, they had come to a time when no one dared speak
his mind, when fierce, growling dogs roamed everywhere, and when you had to
watch your comrades torn to pieces after confessing to shocking crimes.
There was no thought of rebellion or disobedience in her mind.
She knew that even as things were, they were far better off than they had been
in the days of Jones, and that before all else, it was needful to prevent the
return of the human beings.
Whatever happened, she would remain faithful, work hard, carry out the
orders that were given to her, and accept the leadership of Napoleon.
But still, it was not for this that she and all the other animals had hoped and toiled.
It was not for this that they had built the windmill and faced the bullets of Jones's gun.
Such were her thoughts, though she lacked the words to express them.
At last, feeling this to be in some way a substitute for the words she was
unable to find, she began to sing Beasts of England.
The other animals sitting round her took it up, and they sang it three times
over, very tunefully, but slowly and mournfully, in a way they had never sung it before.
They had just finished singing it for the third time when Squealer, attended
by two dogs, approached them with the air [clears throat] of having something important to say.